Guide to the Emery and Elvera Carlson Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Emery and Elvera Carlson Papers
1928-1980
1940-1949
RG 246
Yale University Divinity School Library
1
(2 boxes)
Correspondence, writings, and collected material document the work of Emery W. Carlson and Elvera Teed Carlson, Lutheran missionaries serving in China from 1940 to 1949. Emery Carlson was a medical doctor who worked at the Lutheran Hospital in Xuchang, Henan (Hsuchang, Honan) province from 1941 to 1944. He was active in famine relief work 1942-1944 and in 1945 became an intelligence officer working for the Office of Strategic Services behind Japanese lines in Henan. After the war Carlson returned to the mission hospital but the family was forced to leave China in 1949 due to the Communist takeover.
Carlson, Emery W.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Erleen Carlson Christensen, 2012
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Emery W. and Elvera Teed Carlson were Swedish-American missionaries in China serving under the Evangelical Lutheran Augustana Synod in North America (later known as the Augustana Evangelical Lutheran Church.) Emery Carlson was a medical doctor at the Lutheran Hospital in Hsuchang, Honan province [Xuchang, Henan] from 1941-1944. He was active in famine relief work 1942-1944 and in 1945 served as an intelligence officer for the Office of Strategic Services behind Japanese lines in Honan province. He was allowed to return to his medical work after the war ended but the family was forced to flee when the Communists took control of the province in 1947-1948 and returned to the United States in 1949.
For more detailed biographical information see In War and Famine: Missionaries in China's Honan Province in the 1940s by Erleen Carlson Christensen.
Scope and Contents
These papers, which constitute a major portion of the source material used by Erleen Christensen in writing In War and Famine: Missionaries in China's Honan Province in the 1940s, tell the story of Swedish-American Lutheran missionaries serving in Henan province during a turbulent period in China history. The Sino-Japanese war, Nationalist Communist conflict, banditry, and famine due to crop failures and inflation were dominant forces during the Carlsons' relatively brief but intensive period of work in China.
Series I, Correspondence, is divided into Family and General Correspondence. The Family correspondence contains detailed letters written by the Carlsons to their extended family in the U.S., and well as letters written by Emery to his wife during their wartime separation. Daily life for the family and Emery's medical work are described, as well as the frequent moves and separations occasioned by political events. In the General correspondence section, circular letters written by the Carlsons and letters to/from their mission provide additional documentation, including regarding the American School Kikungshan. For additional documentation regarding the American School Kikungshan, a Lutheran school missionary children, see YDSL Record Group No. 164.
Series II, Writings, includes journals by Elvera and Emery as well as published articles related to the Augustana Evangelical Lutheran Church's work in China.
Series III, Biographical Documentation, includes newspaper clippings about the Carlsons as well as documentation of Emery's work for the OSS during World War II. Series IV, Collected Material, concludes the collection with material related to fellow missionaries, programs, brochures and photos.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1940-1949
II. Writings, 1941-1980
III. Biographical Documentation, 1942-1949
IV. Collected Material, 1928-1970
Lutheran Church -- Missions -- China; Disaster relief -- China; Carlson, Emery W.; Carlson, Elvera Teed; Augustana Evangelical Lutheran Church -- Missions -- China
- Correspondence, 1940-1949; Series I
  - Family correspondence
    - Extended family
      Scope and Contents
      These letters were written by Emery and Elvera Carlson to extended family members in the U.S.
      - Leaving U.S. and travel to China, 1940 Aug-Sep (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Arrival in China; studying Chinese in Peiping (Beijing), 1940 Oct (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Evacuated to Honan (Henan) province to avoid Japanese troops, 1940 Nov (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Travel to Hsuchang, Honan (Xuchang); continuation of language study, 1940 Dec (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Incl. re. mission conference, daily life, 1941 Jan-Feb (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Descriptions of daily life of missionaries, 1941 Mar (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Incl. re. medical work of Emery W. Carlson (EWC), 1941 Apr (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Descriptions of EWC's clinical work, daily life, 1941 May (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Incl. re. difficulty getting supplies, unsettled conditions; description of Chinese Postal Service, 1941 Jun (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Description of hospital care; language exams; Elvera T. Carlson (ETC) teaching English at girls' school, 1941 Jul-Aug (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - EWC takes bicycle trip to Juchow and Loyang to check on medical work; threats from Japanese troops, 1941 Sep-Dec (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Family moves to Juchow in January; EWC only doctor at hospital; visits other stations; daughter Faith Louise born March 12., 1942 Jan-Jun (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Rampant famine and inflation; EWC made chair of relief committee; girl babies being abandoned, 1942 Jul-Dec (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Family moves to Hsuchang; EWC only doctor in mission; much travel by bicycle, treating patients; better harvest brings some relief to famine, 1943 Jan-Dec (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Japanese invasion necessitates move west with dangerous journey; family settles in Chungking (Chongqing); son Jon Paul born July 10, 1944 Jan-Jul (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Waiting in Chungking; EWC takes family to India to await transport to U.S., 1944 Aug-Dec (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - EWC now civilian employee of U.S. Army, returns to Chengtu (Chengdu); ETC and children go to U.S., 1945 Jan-Mar (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - EWC sets up dispensary in Sian (Xian), then Tantouchen, seeing 100 patients daily; when war ends, returns to Honan to re-equip hospital, 1946 Mar (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - EWC on furlough in U.S. with family, then family returns to China, stationed in Hsuchang after delays; threats from Communist troops, 1947 Mar-Dec (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Hsuchang attacked by Communist troops; families moved to Chengchow (Zhengzhou), then Hankow (Wuhan), to await relocation; EWC travels to Kunming to explore establishing new work there, 1948 Jan-Feb (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Carlsons and two other families move to Kunming, 1948 Mar-Jun (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - EWC doing clinical work in government camps for beggars and evangelistic work; son Mark Luther born August 26, 1948 Jul-Dec (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Difficult economic conditions; older daughter Erleen at school in Hong Kong where American School Kikungshan had been evacuated; EWC working at clinic of Municipal Hospital in Kunming; Carlsons return to U.S. where EWC begins medical practice in Nebraska, 1949 Jan-Jun (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Emery to Elvera
      These letters were written by Emery Carlson to his wife when they were separated from each other during wartime.
      - EWC serving as civilian employee of U.S. Army during war; leaves family in India and returns to Chengtu, 1945 Jan-Feb (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Descriptions of EWC's daily life in Chengtu, 1945 Mar (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Incl. re. EWC socializing with other missionaries, some medical work; family has arrived back in U.S., 1945 Apr-Jun (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - EWC seeing about 100 patients daily in Tantouchen, 1945 Jul (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - War ends; EWC considering plans for future; decides to return to Hsuchang via Chungking, 1945 Aug-Sep (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - EWC in Hsuchang; Japanese remaining on mission property, which is in bad condition; Japanese officer lends EWC truck for trip to Sian to get hospital equipment, 1945 Oct (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - Cleaning up hospital in Hsuchang; reorganizing work; many obstacles; longs to be with family, 1945 Nov-Dec (Box 2, Folder 30)
      - EWC on United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration (UNRRA) committee; description of medical work, 1946 Jan-Feb (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - EWC begins trip home to U.S.; waiting for transport in Shanghai; on freighter diverted to Guam, 1946 Mar (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - General Correspondence, 1940-1949
    - Circular letters from Carlsons, 1945 Oct- 1948 Sep (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Augustana Board of Foreign Missions: letters to extended family regarding Carlsons, 1940 Dec- 1949 Jun (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Augustana Board of Foreign Missions: regarding financial matters, 1946 May- 1949 Jun (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Augustana Board of Foreign Missions: bulletins regarding Carlsons and other missionaries, 1943-1948 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - American School Kikungshan: letters regarding school board matters and regarding daughter Erleen, 1949 Jan-Mar (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Letters from Carlsons to/from others, including Alice Karel, Dr. Benson, Arthur Kennedy, Dr. Shih, 1945 Mar-1949 May (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Letters of others, including extended family members and other missionaries, 1942 Oct- 1949 Feb (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Writings, 1940-1980; Series II
  - Published articles, including "Through No Man's Land", "The Bible in China", "A Tour of the Augustana Synod Mission Field in Central Honan", 1941-1947 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Journal of Elvera Carlson: "Impressions of My Work in China", 1940 Aug-1943 Aug (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Journal of Emery Carlson: "The Work in Yunnan Province, China", 194 Aug-1980 Mar (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Biographical Documentation, 1942-1949; Series III
  - Newspaper clippings regarding the Carlsons, 192 Mar - 1948 Oct (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Office of Strategic Services (OSS) documents, including contract of employment, certificate, 1945 Mar-Oct (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Travel documents, innoculations,etc., 1947 Jun - 1949 Jun (Box 2, Folder 45)
- Collected Material, 1928-1970; Series IV
  - Prayer booklet, magazine articles, clippings, photos regarding other missionaries, 1928-1970 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Miscellaneous items, including program, booklets, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 47)